

Microsoft Research, Redmond WA, USA

■ mbrucato@microsoft.com | ★ https://matteo-brucato.github.io/ | ★ MatteoBrucato

## Summary\_

**Senior Researcher** at Microsoft Research, in the Data Systems Group.

Ph.D. from the University of Massachusetts Amherst. Thesis on systems for scalable and easy prescriptive analytics. Thesis title: "Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data".

More than 8 years of experience in research, with several publications in top-tier conferences and journals in data and information management (SIGMOD, VLDB, CACM, VLDBJ). Multidisciplinary research, with publications in top NLP, IR and robotics/AI conferences. Work recognized by several ACM awards (CACM, SIGMOD Highlights, invited VLDBJ, best demos and best paper at VLDB, best young research nominee in RANLP), and several scholarships (Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship by UMass; merit, research and exchange scholarships by the University of Bologna).

More than 8 years of mentorship and advising experience. Mentored more than 20 students, at all levels (undergrad, master, and doctoral students), and directly managed several projects.

Several industrial internships, both as researcher (MSR, IBM) and software developer (Cineca, Maggiore Hospital).

## Research Interests

Research areas: Data Management, Prescriptive Analytics, Decision Making, Stochastic Constrained Optimization, Fair Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Robotics, Natural Language Processing, Information Retrieval.

**Research interests**: Theoretical and systemic aspects of constrained optimization, decision making and prescriptive analytics at a very large scale; Structured, unstructured, and natural query languages; Scalable and approximate algorithms; Systems for interactive data exploration; Scalable systems for fair ML; Scalable systems for AI and robotics; Personalized text summarization.

## Education

**UMASS AMHERST** Amherst, MA, USA

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2013 - 2021

- Co-advisors: Peter J. Haas, Alexandra Meliou, and Azza Abouzied (NYU)
- Thesis: Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA Bologna, Italy 2011 - 2013

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Summa cum laude
- · Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Temporal Information Retrieval

#### **UNIVERSITY OF BOLOGNA**

Bologna, Italy

2008 - 2011

**B.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE** 

- · Summa cum laude
- Thesis Advisor: Danilo Montesi
- Thesis: Mobile systems for patient-reported outcomes

### EXCHANGE PROGRAMS \_\_\_

**ARHUS UNIVERSITY** Århus, Denmark

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING M.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

Jan - Jun 2013

• Advisor: Christian S. Jensen

**UC RIVERSIDE** Riverside, CA, USA

EXCHANGE PROGRAM DURING B.S., COMPUTER SCIENCE

Sep - Jun 2011

• Advisor: Vassilis J. Tsotras

### **Honors & Awards**

2020	Best Demo Award, VLDB 2020	Tokyo, Japan
2020	Best Demo Runner-up Award, VLDB 2020	Tokyo, Japan
2019	Krithi Ramamritham Computer Science Scholarship	Amherst, MA, USA
2018	CACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlights)	Amherst, MA, USA
2017	ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (invited journal paper in SIGMOD Records)	Amherst, MA, USA
2017	Invited journal paper in the VLDB Journal, Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016	Amherst MA USA

2016	Best Papers of, VLDB 2016	New Delhi, India
2013	M.S. with Honors, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2013	Best Young Researcher Award Nominee, RANLP 2013	Hissar, Bulgaria
2013	Merit Scholarship, awarded to 0.2% of all students of the University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Research Scholarship, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2012	Complimentary AAAI Membership, Stanford Online AI Course	Stanford, CA, USA
2011	B.S. with Honors, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2011	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2010	Merit Certificate, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy
2010	Exchange Scholarship, University of Bologna	Bologna, Italy

5 11 . . . .

## **Publications**

- N. Yadav, M. Brucato, A. Fariha, O. Youngquist, J. Killingback, A. Meliou, P. J. Haas SUBSUME: A Dataset for Subjective Summary Extraction from Wikipedia Documents NewSum @ EMNLP 2021 (workshop paper)
- S. B. Nashed, J. Svegliato, M. Brucato, C. Basich, R. Grupen, S. Zilberstein Solving Markov Decision Processes with Partial State Abstractions ICRA 2021
- 3. **M. Brucato**, M. Mannino, A. Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization *VLDB 2020* (demonstration paper) pp.2881-2884
  - Rest Demo Award. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE
- 4. A. Fariha, **M. Brucato**, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou SuDocu: Summarizing Documents by Example **VLDB 2020** (demonstration paper) pp.2861-2864
  - 👭 Best Demo Runner-Up Award. Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZGzF6cBSYjo
- 5. **M. Brucato**, N. Yadav, A. Abouzied, P. J. Haas, A. Meliou Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases *SIGMOD* 2020 pp.269-283
- M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou Scalable Computation of High-Order Optimization Queries Communications of the ACM (CACM) 2019 pp.108-116
- 7. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

Package queries: Efficient and scalable computation of high-order constraints The VLDB Journal 2018 (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016) pp.693-718

8. **M. Brucato**, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou A Scalable Execution Engine for Package Queries

SIGMOD Record 2017 (ACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award 2017) pp.24-31

9. **M. Brucato**, A. Abouzied, C. Blauvelt Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns *arXiv:1706.00070 2017* 

10. **M. Brucato**, J. F. Beltran, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems

VLDB 2016 pp.576-587

- Rest papers of VLDB 2016
- 👭 Invited journal paper in the VLDB Journal (Special Issue on Best Papers of VLDB 2016)
- RACM SIGMOD Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in SIGMOD Records 2017)
- RCACM Research Highlight Award (Invited journal paper in CACM Research Highlight 2018)
- 11. M. Brucato, A. Abouzied, and A. Meliou

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation

**Data4U @ VLDB 2014** (workshop paper) pp.13-18

12. **M. Brucato**, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou

PackageBuilder: From Tuples to Packages

VLDB 2014 (demonstration paper) pp.1593-1596

13. K. Fernandes, **M. Brucato**, R. Ramakrishna, A. Abouzied, A. Meliou PackageBuilder: Querying for packages of Tuples

**SIGMOD 2014** (poster paper) pp.1613-1614

14. M. Brucato, D. Montesi

Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval

ECIR 2014 pp.385-397

 M. Brucato, L. Derczynski, H. Llorens, K. Bontcheva, C. S. Jensen Recognising and Interpreting Named Temporal Expressions RANLP 2013 pp.113-121

👭 Best Young Researcher Award Nominee

## **Professional Experience**

INDUSTRY.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA

SENIOR RESEARCHER

Oct 2021 - present

**Microsoft Research** 

Redmond, WA, USA

RESEARCH INTERN

May - Aug 2017

Worked under the supervision of Kaushik Chakrabarti on natural language to SQL using neural networks.

**IBM Watson** 

T. J. Watson Research Center, Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

Jun - Aug 2016

RESEARCH INTERN, WATSON HEALTH

Worked under the supervision of **Shilpa Mahatma** and **Yajuan Wang** on "conceptual queries" for healthcare applications.

CINECA Casalecchio di Reno, Bologna, Italy

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

Jun - Oct 2012

· Responsible for developing and managing a data warehouse and analytics system for a nationwide videoconferencing system.

 Duties included generating aggregated data and analytics, deployed through usable interfaces to let decision makers understand usage and performance of the videoconferencing system.

Maggiore Hospital Bologna, Italy

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (VOLUNTEER)

2011 - 2013

Co-developed software to help the Emergency Room visit their patients using portable ultrasound technology.

- Software deployed on medical tablets to help doctors collect patient's information on the field.
- The collected data was then used to make better informed decisions in the Emergency Room.

ACADEMIA

## **DREAM Lab, University of Massachusetts**

Amherst, MA, USA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sep 2013 - May 2021

- Working with Prof Peter J. Haas, Prof Alexandra Meliou, and Prof Azza Abouzied (NYU Abu Dhabi) to create Package Builder, a system
  that extends query engines to support the generation of packages, i.e., collections of tuples with global properties that are true of the entire
  collection.
- Technical paper at SIGMOD 2020
- Demo papers at VLDB 2020
- Invited journal paper at CACM Research Highlights 2019.
- Invited journal paper at the VLDB Journal 2018.
- Invited journal paper at SIGMOD Records 2017.
- Technical paper at VLDB 2016; workshop paper and demo paper at VLDB 2014; undergraduate research poster at SIGMOD 2014.
- · Project website: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu.
- DREAM Lab website: dbgroup.cs.umass.edu.
- Project code: Scalable-PaQL-Queries on GitHub

## Design Technology Lab, NYU Abu Dhabi

Abu Dhabi, UAE

VISITING PH.D. CANDIDATE

Mar - May 2016

• Paper: Redistributing Funds across Charitable Crowdfunding Campaigns (arXiv:1706.00070).

AMPLab, UC Berkeley

Berkeley, CA, USA

VISITING PH.D. STUDENT

May - Aug 2015

• Worked on extensions to Package Builder to identify ideal packages by example, under NYU Summer internship.

Data-Intensive Systems Lab, Århus University

Århus, Denmark Jan - Jun 2013

VISITING M.S. STUDENT

- · Worked on M.S. thesis on Temporal Information Retrieval under the supervision of Prof Christian S. Jensen.
- Actively collaborated with researchers within the group.
- · Published two papers in main international conferences in the fields of NLP and IR.

## **Database Lab, UC Riverside**

Riverside, CA, USA

Jan - Jun 2013

Undergraduate Research Intern (volunteer)

• Worked closely with a Ph.D. candidate and Prof Vassilis J. Tsotras on query optimization techniques for query result diversification.

- Developed a query parser for a SQL-like diversification query language.
- Devised and developed a query optimizer to select optimal diversification query plans.
- Developed client/server technology to issue and evaluate diversification queries.

## **Advising & Mentoring**

OCTOBER 18, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO 3

Research Advisor for Ph.D. students Riddho Ridwanul and Anh Mai Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** 2021 Riddho (UMass Amherst) and Anh (NYU Abu Dhabi) are first-year Ph.D. students and working on package queries. Research Advisor for M.S. students Oscar Youngquist and Julian killingback Amherst, MA 2021 Oscar is working on enhanching SuDocu, our system for extractive document summarization by example. Julian helped us collecting user-annotade data from Mechanical Turk. Research Advisor for undergraduate student Agam Sandhu Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** 2020 Agam Sandhu worked on scalable stochastic constrained optimization under costly sampling methods. Research Advisor for PhD student Ahmad Chatha (NYU) Amherst, MA 2020 Ahmad Chatha worked on combining scalable constrained optimization methods with scenario-based methods for stochastic optimization. Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft Research) Amherst, MA Mentored MS students (Abdul Hannan Kanji, Parul Gupta, Ge Gao, Xinlu Liu) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with Microsoft Research, to improve the Fairlearn library (https://fairlearn.github.io). Research Advisor for MS student Kanchi Masalia Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** 2020 Kanchi Masalia worked on parts of SuDocu, our system for personalized efficient document summarization by example. Research Advisor for undergrad Genglin Liu Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** 2020 Genglin Liu worked on the frontend of SuDocu, our system for personalized efficient document summarization by example. Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kyaw Htet Amherst, MA UMASS AMHERST Fall 2019 Kyaw worked on analyzing scenario reductions methods for stochastic optimization. **Project Mentor (in collaboration with Microsoft)** Amherst, MA **UMASS AMHERST** Spring 2019 Mentored a group of four MS students (Katie House, Shanu Vashishtha, Deeksha Razdan, Cheng-Yin Eng) for their Independent Class project (CS 696DS), in collaboration with Microsoft to produce notebooks that showcase their Machine-as-a-service platform Azure ML. **Research Mentor for undergraduate student Nishad Ranade** Amherst, MA UMASS AMHERST 2018-2019 Nishad worked on Monte Carlo scenario reductions methods. Research Mentor for 1st-year PhD student Nishant Yadav Amherst, MA UMASS AMHERST 2018 Nishant and I worked together on stochastic package queries. Research Mentor for graduate student Sandhya Sankaranarayanan Amherst, MA Fall 2015 UMASS AMHERST Sandhya and I worked together on extending the package query language PaQL. **Research Mentor for undergraduate student Kevin Fernandez** Amherst, MA UMASS AMHERST Spring 2014 Kevin and I worked together on evaluation techniques for package queries. This work was invited to present at the ACM SIGMOD 2014 Undergraduate Research Poster Competition. Research Mentor for graduate student Rahul Ramakrishna Amherst, MA

UMASS AMHERST 2013 - 2014

Rahul and I worked together on interface abstractions for package queries. Our work was demonstrated at VLDB 2014.

# **Teaching**

**Teaching Assistant for Graduate Database Systems (CS 645)** Amherst, MA

**UMASS AMHERST** Office hours, question answering, grading, projects.

**Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)** Amherst, MA

Spring 2021

**UMASS AMHERST** Fall 2020

Office hours, question answering, grading and labs.

Teaching Assistant for Undegraduate Class "A Networked World" (INFO 203) **UMASS AMHERST** Homework grading. Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Introduction To Computation (CS 250) Responsible for discussion sessions, occasional lectures, office hours, homework and discussion grading. **Teaching Assistant for Undergraduate Database Systems (CS 345)** Responsible for occasional lectures, project advising, office hours, homework and project grading. Professional Service & Leadership\_ Reviewer • IEEE Transactions of Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE). **Guest Editorial Board** • Information Processing and Management, special issue on Time and Information Retrieval, Elsevier, 2014/2015. **External Review Committee** • VLDB 2017 SIGMOD 2015 VLDB 2015 RANI P 2013 **Lab Seminar Organizer** Amherst, MA, USA UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB • Coordinated weekly discussion seminar, including invited talks and paper readings, for the UMass Amherst Database Research group (~10 Ph.D. students and faculty), and webmaster duties. **Student Seminar Leader** Amherst, MA, USA UMASS AMHERST DATABASE LAB · Organized and coordinated a weekly discussion seminar among Ph.D. and M.S. students in the UMass Amherst Database Research group to foster research collaborations, exchange of ideas, group discussions, and group cohesion. Talks INDUSTRY\_ Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data MEGAGON LABS **Stochastic Package Queries for In-Database Prescriptive Analytics** SISU DATA Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems Redmond, WA, USA MICROSOFT RESEARCH **Conceptual Queries for Multiple Data Sources** Austin, TX, USA **IBM WATSON** Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages Berkeley, CA, USA BERKELEY LABS ACADEMIA. Package Queries: Scalable Prescriptive Analytics Close to the Data Package Queries: Scalable Prescriptive Analytics Close to the Data CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY

Amherst, MA

Amherst, MA Fall 2017

Amherst, MA Fall 2015

2014 - 2015

2013 - 2015

2014 - 2015

Fall 2015

Virtually

Jan 2021

Virtually

Sep 2021

Aug 2016

Jul 2015

Portland, OR, USA (virtually)

Spring 2018

Virtually

Mar 2021

Virtually

Mar 2021

Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data Virtually

HARVARD UNIVERSITY, DASLAB Jan 2021

Stochastic Package Queries For In-database Optimization Under Uncertainty Virtually at INFORMS 2020

INFORMS 2020 Nov 2020 sPaQLTooLs: A Stochastic Package Query Interface for Scalable Constrained Optimization

Tokyo, Japan (virtually)

Sep 2020

• Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1v5KevGKbfE

**Stochastic Package Queries in Probabilistic Databases** 

SIGMOD 2020

Video: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UrEOEplK06I

OCTOBER 18, 2021 MATTEO BRUCATO Package Queries: Enabling Declarative and Scalable Prescriptive Analytics in Relational Data

MIT CSAIL, DATA SYSTEMS GROUP

Cambridge, MA, USA

Feb 2020

Stochastic Package Queries for In-Database Constrained Optimization Under Uncertainty

Cambridge, MA, USA Jan 2020

MIT, NORTH EAST DATABASE DAY, SAMBERG CONFERENCE CENTER

New Delhi, India

**Scalable Package Queries in Relational Database Systems** 

VLDB 2016

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/scalable-paql-presentation-share.pdf

Sep 2016

**Package Queries: From Tuples to Packages** 

Berkeley, CA, USA Jun 2015

AMPLAB, UC BERKELEY

Improving Package Recommendations through Query Relaxation

Hangzhou, China

VLDB 2014

ECIR 2014

Sep 2014

• Slides: packagebuilder.cs.umass.edu/papers/package-recomm-slides-web.pdf

**Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

*Amsterdam, the Netherlands* Apr 2014

**Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

Bologna, Italy

University of Bologna

Dec 2013

**Metric Spaces for Temporal Information Retrieval** 

Århus, Denmark

ÅRHUS UNIVERSITY

Jan 2013